Help you take a lunch to get your eyes big?  It's a costly person, right?  There are more than
幫你晏水來來大眼？ 整個費人這樣不？ 有超過
1.12 million caregivers, and according to estimates from the May 2024 survey
112萬名照顧，根據2024年5月會調查的數字
, more than 260,000 of them are elderly solo caretakers.
估計，當中的年長獨自顧者都超過26萬人。 從
Many of those who have been engaged in excellence and nurturing for many years is one of the examples, she has
事優而育很多年的不少就是其中一個例子，他
done full-grade care, taking care of a 95-year-old, body deterioration,
做了全績的照顧，照顧緊95歲，身體人退化，
eyes can not see things.  I'm going to wash my hands now.  Well,
雙眼看不見東西的媽媽。 我現在去洗手。 好吧 ,
you come on your own, because I don't think he can see anything for you to say gaming is
你自己來好，因為我想他看不到東西對你說打機
very big I am a long wonder player, I myself had it before
很大的我也是一個長奇玩者，我自己之前是有
.  Here, you are waiting for me to go down and buy vegetables.  I see you violently fast
吧。 嗱，你在這裡等我下去買菜。 我看你暴很快
.  So one in the house is heavily
。 所以家裡有一隻重
broken.  It is a tree, not a heavy one.  In this episode of 7 million kinds of
爛。 它是樹，不是一隻重。 今集的700萬種生
life, we come to see how this rat, 247 all this way to take
活，我們就來看看這隻鼠，怎麼247全這樣照
care of the house's orchids.
顧家裡的樹蘭。
Well, our breakfast is the same!  The milk he drinks is
那呢，我們的早餐一樣的了！ 他喝的奶和我
different from the milk I drink.  The milk he drinks this is the nutrition that requires him to drink
喝的奶不同的。 他喝的奶呢就是這樣要求他喝
.
營養 .
People make hot buns this is so is so put, I am to be like this
人家做熱麵包呢是這樣是這樣擺的嘛，我是要這樣
, because he does not have island sweat, so the sweat will not िर to
樣，因為它沒有島汗水，那麼一些汗水就不會िर到
the plate, so this my position is following him
那碟，所以呢我的位子也是跟著他的需要來看清
.  Two years ago slowly
。 兩年前 慢慢
earning, and itself still can buy cooking, looking after the whole family, to
賺，又本身都還有可以買煮飯，看著全家，去
every Miss work of the contract is coming to an end, with family members after discussing, than
逢小姐工作的合約就來完結，跟家人商量之
decided to settle down  Take care of, get
後，就決定比安奴，自己成為喘職的照顧，每
up at 8am every day and then start the rolling life of his T, so so
日早上8點起床後就展開渠T的碌生活，咁
I get it done, after these things, it's almost time to
所以我搞定，這些事情之後呢，就才差不多時
ask him to get up.  That I will think he is he is trying to match
間就叫他起來囉。 也就是我會覺得他是他是盡量
with me so the things in life are going to change according to his needs
跟我配合的 所以生活情的東西是會按著他的需要
and his changes.  Minor
和它的變化來到變化囉。 小
failure and the initial cognitive outside, the leg also has nothing out to sit on the
衰竭和初期的認知外，隻腳也沒什麼出要坐
argument.  Things are also slowly deteriorating, and now the eyes can no longer see anything
論。 事情也在慢慢退化，現在雙眼已經看不見東西
.  Suddenly it fell a lot.  After coming out this is not very
吧。 突然之間跌的很多囉。 出了之後呢不是好
talkative, so great is often sleeping hobby.  His other senses are making appointments
講到事情，那正是整天睡覺興趣。 他其他感官也
so you can you rely on second d senses to save that society's
約緊 所以你可以 你靠第二D感覺救回那個社的
problems, for him it may not be able to do it
問題，對他來說就未必做得到吧
.  Often feel that they are useless, but not dead can he yeah
。 常常覺得自己沒用囉，可是又不死得囉他呀
so we say these days have no choice.   Do what you can
那我們說這些日子沒得選擇嘛。
every day.  Help you get into the water in the afternoon.
每天能做的事就做。 幫你晚進水。
Because of this he has a
因為這他有一支
6 times, at night must be
6次，晚上要
at eight o'clock must have to
一定是八點鐘 一定就要
twin my first time is when I will remember wrong and will not be confused
孖住我第一次是什麼時候的 我會記錯和會不會亂
, so I have to make a table I remember this but do
，所以我要做一個表呢幫自己記住囉，但是時
not remember it  Got ắn.  What, you want to get up the animal and sit for a while
我也不記得了ắn呀。 什麼呀，你想起來牲坐一會兒
, sit down, get up.
，坐吧，起來吧。
Usually I ignore him.  Because he can handle it himself.
通常我不管他的吧。 因為他自己搞得掂的。 一
Firstly, his character this gives him the feeling that he still has some
來他的性格呢 來比他感覺他仍然有點
things that depend on the world.  In fact, he is a very good way
樣東西都依賴世人囉。 其實他也是一個很有辦法
to solve the problem of the person he got up when he got up when he got up
去解決問題的人來的他起來的時候這起來呀
, so he will himself in this window by the side of the tie adjust awake
嘛，那他又會自己在這個窗戶哪裡綁調醒呢讓自
, so that he can easily hold him  body  You
己揸住，噉佢就可以遮住你容易啲氣身喇。 你
can't see if the cup is
看不去的杯子有
tied, because he can't tell which one is him, so he can
紮住的，因為他分不反哪個是他的嘛，那咪
touch it.
摸到囉。
You go to interject this he does not want you
你走去插手呢 他不要你的
this, he has a finger to hold things so, so he has one side of
這，他有一隻手指要扶東西吧那，所以他有一邊
this you are to help him comb.  I'll help you a few times
這你是要幫她梳的。 我幫你兩下
, so you can put it.   At
好，得畀你擺。
this point my breakfast is not much better should.
這時候我的早餐差不多了吧應該。
[Music]
[音樂]
Things
事
on twice I cool once, because my cold.
就兩次我就涼一次，因為我個冷。
I myself have it
我自己本身有
, and have egg alcohol so and because I myself had it before
噶，並且有蛋醇這樣並且因為我自己之前是有啦
, so the doctor prescribed some sea
那麼，所以還是醫生開了一些海
15800.  15800?
15800。 15800呀？
Oops, 158 is missing. I tried this one.   is
哎 不少了158的喔 這一試過。
the date ok?  Not if you eat and drink water every day yes yes the
D約可以嗎？ 不然如果你天天吃喝水吧 是是的
heart
粒心臟
this.  Blood
這粒。 血
лед
лед
[Music]
[音樂]
How about that?  The bad here, here.
這不？ 這裡的不好呀，這裡。
Hey, so let's do some simple physical and mental exercises.  Okay, a pat on the
嗱，那我們做點簡單的意身運動先。 好啦，拍
head.  Count for yourself.
個頭。 自己數下。
[Music]
[音樂]
Let me watch YouTube every day.  Those Chinese medicine doctors teach this, it turns out
畀我天看YouTube呀。 那些中醫師教呢，原來
this position has to be shot Yes
這個位置也要拍啊 是的
[Music]
[音樂]
You remind me, pay the management fee, I'm afraid I forget.
你提我下，交管費，我怕我不記得了。
In fact, time
其實
will be at home rest a lot will depend on the mother's body situation
時間都會在家休不少 就會視媽媽體的情況
, then take him down the street three or buy and send
，再帶他下街三部或者買送
fish can not see things after, when out on the street, the girl's
魚看不見東西之後，出街時，女就成了他的
eyes become what the day  What scenery does the street have?  Hit the
眼睛，那天天氣，怎麼樣條街有什麼風景？ 撞到邊
side of the street, many will be described in his side.  We are now
街方，不少都會在它以邊這樣形容。 我們現在
ready to pay the management fee first, and then to the market.  Wow, I have
準備去交管理費先，然後之後去街市。 嘩，好久
n't seen the sun in a long time.  It has been raining all these days.  Right now is the
沒見過個陽光呀。 這幾天全部都在下雨。 宜家
most visible sun. Closer than this?  Many shops sell them on the street. They
就最見得多個太陽了吧近過呢？ 街上很多小店都在賣
all like plants.  He still has some things to talk about when this
架嘛也喜歡植物的。 他還有點事來說時候呢想
thinking he went to see this earlier, I can not see.  So you feel a bit
住他前些去看呢，我也看不見。 那你就覺得有
frustrated frustrated is like nothing can be done so yourself
一些沮喪沮喪就是好像沒有什麼事情可以做得那樣囉自己
.
。
For us, on the one hand, we have to respond to its changes, and
在我們來說，我們一方面要去應他的變化吧，
then we have to think of some ways to make it every time
而來也要想一些辦法如何能讓他每一路
.
囖。
Hey, you wait for me here.  I'm going down to buy.  White.
嗱，你在這裡等我。 我下去買。 白色呀。
Good morning, I need to order the dish.  24 Well thank you, bye
早晨呢，要個菜點埋呀心。 24 好不該曬，拜拜
.
。
Oops, I want to ask you this you want to eat pork patties tonight you want to eat ribs.
哎，想問你呢你今晚想吃豬肉餅你想吃排骨。
good .  I see you violent.  Me, I am I am eating rats so
很可以。 我見你暴。 我，我是我也是吃鼠呀所以
.   Wow
。
!  He once said he wanted to commit suicide.
哇 ! 他曾經說過想自殺的
I said you didn't even think about it. If you don't die,
我說你想都沒想呀不死得你還慘呀，和個生
no one knows.  But don't risk yourself.
命完沒人知道啊嘛。 但是就不要搏自己囉。
Because I don't want to slow down, sometimes many years the park won't go
因為不想慢慢，有時候不少年公園都不會去，直
until I do some simple exercise on the back stairs.
至在後樓梯那裡做一點簡單的運動。
If I go to buy, or I I have to do my own things
如果我去買的話，或者我我要做過我自己的事情
, for example, see a doctor
，譬如看醫生呀
, buy things ah so, do not do not do not have to leave this one at home
，買東西啊這樣子，咪不是是不是要留這一個在家
, very ഥ.  It's hard, he has to take responsibility for his life.
囖，好ഥ。 難，他也要為他的生命負責的嘛。
Uh, he can't, he I might have someone he can depend on
誒，他不能，他我可能有人可以讓他依賴曬
.  So actually I'm worried, but I think.  I can not
。 那其實我擔心的，但是我覺得. 我又不能
24 hours a day 36 days a year and
一天24小時一年36天跟
then he himself said he would dispel these relatives.
住他自己都說自己會消心這些親。
As care, not less to change with the situation, and there are different
作為照顧，不少要隨著情況的變化，而有不同
stages above the adaptation.  He said that he himself is urgent and
階段上面的適應。 他說自己個人本身急又高要
demanding, so the process of getting along and communicating with his mother needs to be constantly
求，所以和媽媽相處和溝通的過程需要不斷
regulated in this way.  There are disputes such as this midnight 3 he has an
這樣調節。 爭執有的 譬如這半夜3間他有一次
o'clock this called me, so I ask things.  He asked me how I am now
點鐘呢喊了我，那我問事呀。 他問我現在的如何
, so I was angry I need to know how I am doing now I'm sleeping, you
，那我就生氣 我要知道現在怎麼辦嗎嗻我在睡覺呀，你
wake me up I can't go back to sleep he, in fact, in his case, he
叫醒我睡不回來了她，其實在她來說呢，她是
can't tell the difference between day and night.
無法區分日與夜的。
You take care of this alone, do not ask yourself to be perfect
你自己一個照顧呢，不要要求自己perfect囉
, because there are some things you are alone on your own.  There are
，因為有些事情你事上你自己也是一個人。 都有
your own emotions can not be confirmed.  If you cover it hard
你自己的情緒不能實囉。 如果你硬冚住的話
, it is likely that the pressure will be greater.  You have to tell
這，很可能那個壓力就會越大的。 你也要說給
him where your limits are, suddenly there is water.
他聽你，你的限制在哪裡囉，突然間有水。
So my younger brothers and sisters are very helpful, I have one, every
那我的弟弟妹妹都很help的，我有一個呢，每個禮
Saturday comes here to cook and eat, my younger brother this past our two floors
拜六都來這煮飯吃的，我弟弟這他膏我們兩層
this afternoon
樓這晚
for him.
畀他的。
dish .  meat and is to eat this red bean rice, I and you make back a little hot
菜。 肉和是吃這個紅豆飯，我跟你整回熱一點
better yeah in
好呀
your mind m is a how character of?
你心目中的m咪一個怎樣性格的？
Bandage it.
紮吧。
Cooking food I found out that he does not eat a lot of things potatoes do not eat it
煮東西我才知道原來他很多東西不吃呀 薯仔不吃啦
spinach does not eat it, fruit is not sweet not eat it.
菠菜不吃啦，水果不甜的不吃啦。
He didn't like soup, but
他原來不喜歡喝湯的，可是他以前他自己煮那
he used to have boiled soup for us to drink when he cooked it himself.  Maybe being a mother is to
一陣子他有滾湯給我們喝個喔。 也許做媽媽呢就
put their own requirements to the lowest, now reversed
就把自己的要求放到放到最低吧，現在調轉了
the role to know chicken you were young I heard you are in a good water frame right you
個角色才知道雞你小時候聽說你在條好水啊你小時候
young, in the three good water
哎呀，在條好水啊穿三位水
you have a beautiful position?  Because the cloth pot head with
為什麼你有漂亮三隻的？ 因為布煲頭配
a set of belly is very beautiful so yeah do not roll all over the
一套肚子很漂亮 那別週身滾
old do not
老也不
brothers and sisters no sun, his parents have left one after another, so so
兄弟姊妹沒曬啦，他爸媽都相繼離開，那所
often the family is scattered, because it becomes a big life
以一整天家庭就散掉了，個生活變化很大啦，
He is very well-learned,
因為要走爛呢，沒法讀書啦 他是很好學的，我
when we were young, we saw him in the newspaper to read it, for a while you
她們小的時候都見他會報報紙看的，一會兒你
pay attention to this, the iron on the door is written on it,
留意一下呢，門口鐵那裡寫著，記得喊鑰匙這是
he remembers the lock  It makes me much better.
他寫的，他們自讓我很多的。
In growing up, he contributed a lot to the family,
在長大的過程裡，他對家庭的貢獻很大的，
we have 4 brothers and sisters, so if only my father
我們有4個兄弟姊妹啦，那如果只有我爸爸
worked alone, this life.  It can be maintained.
一個人做事的話，這個生活。 可以維持得到。
But it will not be very full of it, so so he has to take advantage of us when we go to school
但是就不會很充囉，那所以他也要趁我們上學
, he will go to do it.  Yeah take care of you well or not
那時候，他會去做的。 呀，照顧得你好不好呀
, smell you good or not, good.  No good me, no good me no
，臭得你好不好好呀，好。 不要我，不要我不
good today.
好今天呢。
[Music]
[音樂]
Life is not your control, you can't destroy it yourself,
生命不是你控制的，你不能自己去破壞它，
but not very strong flow if the time is to go.
但是如果到時候是要走的話，不要很強流。
I think we all have a very consistent view of life
我想我們大家對生命這東西的看法都很一的這樣
, so what clothes he wears on the video, what shoes he wears, he
，所以他上片呀穿什麼衣服呀穿什麼鞋呀那些，他完
completely talked about it and took care of it in the
全部說曬了
morning  Quite a lot of
單一個早上已經看到照顧和一時間要處理多少
things ton good mother after not a few sisters finally have their own usually his
樣野頓好媽之後不少姐終於有自己的平時她最
favorite is at home reading books online shopping play phone games and then free d it
中意 在家看看書 網購 玩下電話遊戲 再有空吧
will take some collected meat 20 years of appreciation
喔就會拿一些收藏了十幾20年的肉氣精出來欣賞
You classify it so there is a long time to play with the shape, the material category
你把它分類這樣也有排玩了用形狀吧，質料類
, do the style well, and have a carving work, enough ancient frame,
吧、做型好吧，和有個雕工吧，夠古樸囉，
for example, this piece is in Hainan, now is very difficult  Yes,
譬如這這件是海南啦，回來那時候是很難的啊，
some people no longer recognize it as a Hainan treasure
但是現在已經是有人已經不認得他是海南寶了
, but when you look at it, you look at you is you can see it
了，可是你照他的時候，你看看嚇你是你是看到
inside it?  Although not a little long to help himself create private time,
它裡面有落的嗎？ 雖然不少長幫自己製私人時間，
but he is frank that after becoming a full caregiver, friends pour manuals are
但是他也坦然，做了全顧者後，朋友倒手冊
difficult for a similar social life.
很難為似的社交生活。
I have a chance.  When I was dating someone, he hoped that I could
我有機會。 約別人的時候呢，他也希望我可
go out and get in touch with them.  I can go until 12 o'clock before, but I have to be back
以出去跟別人接觸。 前也可以去到12點，但是
before 5:30. In recent years, he has participated in the Finance Council
我五點半前要回來了，近年他參加了財會
's peace and quiet program, which
的安寧還計劃，這個計劃會在社區和安院提
includes community services and the safety of the home  Physical care, deep social and spiritual
公晚長者的安寧服務，包括身體照顧、深社靈
support.  There are also other professional teams such as social workers
故的支援。 裏面也有社工等的其他專業團隊
, in the evening the elderly and caregivers encounter any problems, can get a branch
，晚長者和顧者遇到什麼問題，都能得到支
, relieve them a lot of stress.  Your person is going to because really
，緩他們不少的壓力。 你個人是會 因為真的
feel that as a eh take care of said, this his own police character to be
覺得作為一個誒照顧的說，這他自己的警性要
very high to mention that he is in need of help, I have to go out to do part-time,
很高囉要提出他是需要幫助囉，我要出去做兼
if I become a friend  Come down to see
啦、若一些朋友吃飯呀，變了我就沒有人下來看得
him this he can help me find some care Come up to watch him,
到他這他也可以幫我找一點照顧上來看著他，
so I will be more relieved when I go out.
那我出去就會放心一點了。
Hello Miss.  Yes, hello.
您好呀不小姐。 是，你好呀。
Ok, I pay.  I please.
好，我費。 我不該。
There are people.  Little
有人呀。 小
[music]
[音樂]
tired, you are.  to get
累了，你是的。 去
tired  Only come.
累的。 只來吧。
How many muscles.  Come now and get it.
多少筋啊。 馬上來得到了。
In fact, we have been observing the
其實我們一路都觀察著
psychological level all the way, or whether there will be some need in his social spirit
滴心理層面吧，或者是他社交靈上會不會有點
.  So we will also provide support services to my
需要囉。 那我們同時也會提供支援服務給阿
daughter, that she is as care, are one of our concerns
女吧，也就是她是作為照顧，也是我們關注的之
.  In fact, sometimes it is very difficult, one person to see only so
一來的。 其實有時候很難，一個人去照只能這樣
full.  We hope that through different activities, they
全。 我們就希望是透過不同的活動吧，他們也
can also that walk to the street, not just transported in the house
都可以即是走到出街，不只是運著在家裡
inside the house, for example, he used to go to the garden, so now the ice
裡面，譬如說誒他以前是去過冰頭花園，那呀
head  The garden is no longer here, and when we go in to freeze our
，當然現在冰花園不在了，我們進去凍
memories, we are thinking of
憶下時，我們又想著透過可能誒不同的刺激吧
building some happy memories through the possible eh different stimuli.  Knowing that he likes
，建立一些開心的回憶。 知道他原來也喜歡按
massages, so they found a job this is doing aromatherapy those up and
摩喔，那他們就找到一個工作呢是做香薰那些上
do massage with him, so that volunteer is very very good very attentive
來跟他做按摩囉，那那個義工非常的好呀好小
so he is very happy.  Hello there.
心啦 那他很開心。 您好呀。
Siu
小
Ming's voice is your head clear?
明得把聲你的頭通嗎？
huge .  A lot of right so we better today's article scare d not first we one each one
很多 . 好多喔 那我們不如今天文嚇一點未先下我
a stick, holding this first.  Haven't asked about this flavor
們一人一人一支，揸著這先。 沒問過啊這口味
.  What scents do you like?  what scents do you like?  White and
。 你喜歡什麼香味？ 你喜歡什麼香味嗎？ 白而
that scent is not white flower හන් dislike?
那種香味是嗎 白花හන්不喜歡?
Е이터 Don't like it?   I'll
Е이터 不喜歡？
press it for you
幫你按
.
吖嘛可以啊。
Many good has been done to long.  After working for 13 years
不少好已經做到長。 工作了13年後
Magnetic America has now delivered to a new world.  He said this kind of risk-taking
磁美國有現在交到一個新世界。 他說這種打冒
spirit, in fact, with his mother very late.  Before life is so exciting to that is
險的精神，其實和媽媽很晚。 以前人生那麼精彩
these few years to wait for a ພ of it, do not say that
去到也就是這幾年就等一個ພ的吧，有沒有說那個
resistance
抗
feel this walk to the water column this again look up when, today I am in this
覺得這行到水柱呢就再看起時，今天我在這條
running road to here you know the next day not running.
跑道到這裡你怎麼知道我明天的跑道不是第二條呢。
Every day I have to try to live it as well as possible.
每一天我都要盡量過好他。
I think doing people's things and walking is just, if your journey comes
我覺得做人的事情而行的而已，如果你的歷程來到
here to encounter some, such things, you have to face it!
這裡遇到一些，這樣的事情，你就要面對了！
So this picture book was one of my very big times, I don't know if
那這圖書也是我其中一個很大的時候，我不知道
you have read this book.  Talk about a child, let's
你們有看過這本書。 說一個孩子呢，就在和
become friends with this tree, the relationship they have is very
這一棵樹成為朋友吧，他們有的關係東西非常之
good.  This child has grown up so every time he encounters
好的 . 這小孩長大了 那他每一次遇到困
difficulties this he will come back to find this tree This tree this will
難的時候呢 他也會回來找這棵樹 這棵樹這也會
help him solve a little difficulty.
幫他解決大一點的困難。
Sell ​​all those apples, the
賣掉那些蘋果吧，
branches come to build houses, make boats, all their own things contribute contribute
樹枝來建房子了，做船吧，把所自己自己所有的
to this child this finally left this tree head
野貢貢獻打給這小子呢最後剩下這個樹頭
finally this friend this is because this child is back  There is nothing for
最後呢，這小子也回來找他呢就是因為
him.  He had no choice but to spend the rest of their lives together with another tree
他什麼都沒有啦。 他唯有最後呢，就是和另一棵樹
book.
書這一起共到他們的餘生囉。
You will associate with going back to your own home.  In the end the family will always
你會聯想回到你自己的家。 到到最後 家庭永遠
be the branch behind you.   The
都是你背後的支處囉。
needs and threads of care in society are easily overlooked.  In addition
社會上照顧的需要和緒都很容易被忽略。 除
to peace and tranquility also plan he also left will mutually Korean support plan, for
了安寧還計劃他也了會互道韓者支援計劃，為
care assistance, support their care process needs, including for
照顧援，支持他們照顧過程的需求，包括為他
them to evaluate and provide
們評估並提供的建議，
some advice to the community  Referral, care training, care
找一些社區資源和轉介，照顧的訓練，照顧
history planning and
歷的規劃和
also have elders ಡೆ
也都有長者ಡೆ
risk work, so that they in a busy life have still have ime do things
冒務，讓他們在忙碌的生活也還有ime做的事
in the mind or this plan to care for the elderly  That is,
這個計畫照顧中心，胡老者有需要的長者或
social people can participate, so as to "take care of the stress relief, we
是社會人士都能參與，求給”照顧緩壓力，
can return once. Do
大家都可以回一回。
you know, recently I encountered a lot of a lot of scams
你知道呢，最近我遇到好多好多騙案喔。 他
100,000 or 80,000
這次他叫我樂姑娘呀沒錢呀，你入住10萬八萬
for me first.
畀我先啦。 呀。 我們的戶口也沒錢呀。 我轉頭